<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Go on TheAbdusalam - that somali dev</title><link>https://theabdusalam.github.io/tags/go/</link><description>Recent content in Go on TheAbdusalam - that somali dev</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://theabdusalam.github.io/tags/go/atom.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Navigating DDD Complexities[Aggregates]</title><link>https://theabdusalam.github.io/2023/11/20/navigating-ddd-complexities/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://theabdusalam.github.io/2023/11/20/navigating-ddd-complexities/</guid><description>Mastering Domain-Driven Design in Go: A Comprehensive Guide # Introduction # Go, also known as Golang, has gained significant popularity for its simplicity, efficiency, and scalability. In this blog, we will explore the synergy between Go and Domain-Driven Design (DDD), a powerful approach to software development that aligns business requirements with the codebase. By combining the strengths of Go and DDD, developers can build robust, maintainable, and scalable systems.
Understanding Domain-Driven Design (DDD) # Core Concepts of DDD # Ubiquitous Language: Establish a shared vocabulary between business stakeholders and developers to ensure a common understanding of the domain.</description></item><item><title>Diamond Interface Composition in Go</title><link>https://theabdusalam.github.io/2023/10/21/the-diamond-interface-dilemma/</link><pubDate>Sat, 21 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://theabdusalam.github.io/2023/10/21/the-diamond-interface-dilemma/</guid><description>Diamond Interface Composition in Go: A Masterpiece Unveiled # Architecture is an art form. It requires creativity, vision, and an eye for detail. As developers, we should strive to create elegant and expressive code. But what if we could take it a step further? What if we could create code that is not only beautiful but also reusable and flexible?
The Diamond Dilemma # In the realm of Go, interfaces are a powerful tool for achieving abstraction and polymorphism.</description></item></channel></rss>